Chapter 6. The street.
If I had been astonished at first catching a glimpse of so outlandish an
individual as Quiquake circulating among the polite society of a civilized town,
that astonishment soon departed upon taking my first daylight stroll through
the streets of New Bedford. In thorough affairs nei the docks any considerable
seapport will frequently offer to view the queerest looking nond-escripts from
foreign parts. Even in Broadway and chestnut streets Mediterranean mariners
will sometimes jostle the afrighted ladies. Regent street is not unknown to
lascars and melees. And at Bombay in the Apollo green live Yankees have often
scared the natives. But New Bedford beats all Water Street in whopping. In
these last mentioned haunts you see only sailors, but in New Bedford actual
cannibals stand chatting at street corners, savages outright, many of whom
yet carry on their bones unholy flesh.
It makes a stranger stare.
But besides the Fijians, Tonga Deborars, Aromangoans, Panangians, and Brigians, and besides
the wild specimens of the whailing craft, which unheated reel about the
streets, you will see other sites still more curious, certainly more comical.
Their weekly arrive in this town, scores of green verters and New Hampshiremen,
all a thirst for gain and glory in the fishery. They are mostly young, of
stalwart frames, fellows who have felled forests, and now seek to drop the axe
and snatch the whale lance. Many are as green as the green mountains whence they
came. In some things you would think them but a few hours old. Look there,
that chap struting around the corner. He wears a beaver hat and swallowtailed
coat, girdled with a sailor belt and sheath knife. Here comes another with a
southwester and a bombazine cloak.
No town bred dandy will compare with a country bred one. I mean a downright
bumpkin dandy. A fellow that in the dog days will mow his two acres in buckskin
gloves for fear of tanning his hands.
Now when a country dandy like this takes it into his head to make a distinguished
reputation and joins the great whale fishery, you should see the comical
things he does upon reaching the seapport. In bespeaking his sea outfit,
he orders bell buttons to his waist coats, straps to his canvas trousers.
Ah, poor hay seed, how bitterly will burst those straps in the first howling
gale when thou art driven straps button and all down the throat of the tempest.
But think not that this famous town has only harpooners, cannibals, and bumpkins
to show her visitors. Not at all. Still New Bedford is a queer place. Had it not
been for us whalemen, that tract of land would this day perhaps have been in as
howling condition as the coast of Labrador, as it is, parts of her back
country are enough to frighten one. They look so bony. The town itself is perhaps
the dearest place to live in in all New England. It is a land of oil, true
enough, but not like Canaan, a land also of corn and wine. The streets do not run
with milk, nor in the springtime do they pave them with fresh eggs. Yet in spite
of this, nowhere in all America will you find more patrician-like houses, parks,
and gardens more opulent than in New Bedford. Whence came they how planted
upon this once scraggy skoria of a country. Go and gaze upon the iron
emblematical harpoons round yonder lofty mansion, and your question will be
answered. Yes, all these brave houses and flowery gardens came from the
Atlantic, Pacific, and Indian Ocean. One and all they were harpooned and dragged
up hither from the bottom of the sea.
Can her Alexander perform a feat like that? In New Bedford, fathers, they say,
give whales for the for dowers to their daughters and portion off their nieces
with a few porpuses a piece. You must go to New Bedford to see a brilliant
wedding, for they say they have reservoirs of oil in every house, and
every night recklessly burn their lengths in spermicetti candles. In
summertime the town is sweet to see, full of fine maples, long avenues of
green and gold. And in August, high in air, the beautiful and bountiful horse
chestnuts candalabra wise profer the passer by their tapering upright cones
of congregated blossoms.
So omnipotent is art, which in many a district of New Bedford has superinduced
bright terraces of flowers upon the barren refuge rocks thrown aside at
creation's final day. And the women of New Bedford, they bloom like their own
red roses, but roses only bloom in summer, whereas the fine carnation of
their cheeks is perennial as sunlight in the seventh heavens. Elsewhere match
that bloom of theirs you cannot save in Salem where they tell me the young girls
breathe such musk their sailor sweethearts smell them miles offshore as
though they were drawing nigh the odorous malucas instead of the puritanic sands